A Guide to the John S. and James L. Knight Foundation records, Program Files (Non-Grant), RG 5 FA1799
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Program-Related Files, 1975-2019; 6; 32.9 Cubic Feet 94 containers
  - Community Initiatives/Cities Program, 1975-2010; 3; 5.7 Cubic Feet 12 letter document boxes and 6 half boxes.
    - Advisory Committee Files, 1986-2001; 3.1
      - Cities Program Correspondence, 1988 March 29 (Box 1, Folder 3)
        Letter from C.C. Gibson to the Community Foundation of Southeastern Michigan about establishing a fund for them, and about Dave Lawrence becoming the Community Advisor, 1988.
      - Cities Program Correspondence, Advisory Committee Guidelines, 1992 January 16-May 15 (Box 1, Folder 4)
        Knight File Number - 1896
        Cities Program Correspondence, including Advisory Committee Guidelines, 1992.
      - Letters from Community Advisers, 1992 July 31-1993 March 22 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
        Knight File Number - 2106
        Letters from community advisors, requested by Jim Spaniolo, to provide background information for new community liaison, Linda Raybin, contain an overview of their communities and the process used in reviewing grant requests for the Foundation. (2 folders]
      - Cities Program Correspondence, 1993 February 25-1994 April 18 (Box 1, Folder 7)
        Knight File Number - 1897
        Cities Program Correspondence, including program objectives and Advisory Committee list, 1993.
      - Meeting Minutes, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
        Knight File Number - 1057
      - Cities Program Correspondence, 1994-1997 August (Box 1, Folder 10)
        Knight File Number - 1898
        List of members and terms of the Community Initiatives Advisory Committee, 1994-1997.
      - Preparatory Materials for Meeting, 1994 February 4 (Box 1, Folder 11)
        Knight File Number - 1072
        Preparatory materials for the meeting of the Community Initiatives Advisory Committee, 2/4/94. Includes minutes from the conference call meeting (8/27/91), a draft statement on the role of the committee, an article on youth violence interventions, and other columns on youth violence.
      - Preparatory Materials for Meeting, 1995 March 24 (Box 1, Folder 12)
        Knight File Number - 1071
        Preparatory materials for the meeting of the Community Initiatives Advisory Committee. Includes materials which address youth violence and discuss Knight Foundation's role in the problem.
      - Preparatory Materials for Meeting, 1995 May 5 (Box 1, Folder 13)
        Knight File Number - 1073
        Preparatory materials for the meeting of the Community Initiatives Advisory Committee, 5/5/95. Includes minutes of the CI Advisory Committee meeting of 3/24/95, transparency copies from the meeting, a paper on the use of the family preservation model with juvenile offenders, and materials on job training programs to promote social competence in older at-risk adolescents.
      - Preparatory Materials for Meeting, 1995 May 24 (Box 1, Folder 14)
        Knight File Number - 1074
        Preparatory materials for the meeting of the Advisory Committee. Includes agenda, sections on the CI Program and evaluation from KF's strategic plan, charts with breakdown of CI grants by area of special interest (1992-94), a draft statement on the role and mission of the Committee, articles on youth violence prevention programs, and info. on a grant request from the Community Anti-Drug Coalitions of America.
      - Meeting Minutes, 1995 June 1-2 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Cities Program Correspondence, 1996 March 6-1997 February 17 (Box 1, Folder 16)
        Knight File Number - 3903
        Cities Program Correspondence, including invitations to members to continue their work on the committee.
      - Meeting Minutes, 1998 May 14-15 (Box 1, Folder 17)
        Knight File Number - 1705
        Minutes of the meeting of the Community Initiatives Advisory Committee in Miami, FL.
      - Meeting Minutes, 1996 January 22-23 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Meeting Minutes, 1997 May 28-29 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Meeting Minutes, 1997 October 13-14 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Cities Program Correspondence, 1998 July 6-1999 September 20 (Box 1, Folder 21)
        Knight File Number - 3904
        Cities Program Correspondence, including letters from members of the advisory committee responding to Hodding Carter's request for input re: committee membership, needs assessment, the application process, and operating in communities without advisors.
      - Meeting Minutes, 1998 May 14-15 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Meeting Minutes, 1999 September 9 (Box 1, Folder 23)
        Knight File Number - 1704
      - Cities Program Correspondence, 2000 February 1-2001 January 18 (Box 1, Folder 24)
        Knight File Number - 3905
        Cities Program Correspondence, including information on a grid of national organizations working in Knight Communities, an upcoming community initiatives advisory committee meeting, and a request to start implementing the new KF strategy in Centre County, Pennsylvania.
      - Meeting Minutes, 2000 February 22-23 (Box 1, Folder 25)
        Knight File Number - 1689
        Minutes of the meeting of the Community Initiatives Advisory Committee, held in Miami, FL.
    - Initiatives - Community Foundations (donor-advised), 1985-2010; 3.2
      The Community Foundations Initiative (Donor-Advised Funds).Broad community needs in Knight cities were the focus of the grants that Knight Foundation awarded to community foundations, which then distributed the funds locally as needed. The files contain correspondence between Knight Foundation, the community foundations, and community advisors. Guidelines, agreements and memos describe the size and scope of the program, and the financial results of investments. Also included is consultant Eugene Struckhoff's report entitled "Knight Foundation and Community Foundations in Knight Cities," dated 1991. More detailed information about this initiative can be found in the grant files for the individual community foundations.
      - Community Foundations (Donor-advised Funds), 1985 June 18-1996 December 13 (Box 1, Folder 1-37)
        Knight File Number - 268
        Community Foundation files are divided first by year, then alphabetical by city. Folders include correspondence, memos, guidelines and reports relating to donor-advised funds of community foundations. A donor-advised fund is one in which the donor (the Knight Foundation) may make recommendations on how its donated funds are distributed by the Community Foundation which has received them.
      - Community Foundations (Donor-advised Funds), 1985 June 18-1996 December 13 (Box 2, Folder 1-23)
      - Updates on Donor-Advised Funds at Community Foundations, 1995 June 9-1997 November 24 (Box 2, Folder 24)
        Knight File Number - 3291
        Memos from Penny McPhee and Jim Spaniolo to the Board of Trustees re: the Board's request to know if the Knight Funds were meeting the performance criteria set forth in the establishing agreements and grants; and an undated draft of an editorial, written by Larry Meyer, on Community Foundation/Newspaper relationships.
      - Memos, 1993-1999 (Box 2, Folder 25-27)
      - Memos, 2001 January 18-2003 March 13 (Box 3, Folder 1)
        Knight File Number - 4656
        Correspondence and memos re: Community Foundation report drafted by The Conservation Company; annual summaries from several community foundations; and notification of a grant made by the Akron Community Foundation.
      - Community Foundation Meeting, 2002 September 24 (Box 3, Folder 2)
        Knight File Number - 4640
        Meeting materials for participants at a meeting in Atlanta, Georgia. Contains agenda, history of KF, mission and organizational goals statement, donor-advised fund application, and sample fund agreement.
      - Knight Foundation Donor-Advised Funds: Frequently Asked Questions, 2004 July 29 (Box 3, Folder 3)
        Knight File Number - 4641
        Distributed to potential grantees.
      - Donor-Advised Funds Quarterly Report, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 4)
        Knight File Number - 5075
        List of KF Community Foundations who provided grants in 2010 and details of the recipients of donor-advised funds, including project description and amount.
    - Initiatives - Immunization, 1993-2000; 3.3
      This sub-series consists of letters from Community Advisors regarding the needs in their communities.
      - Community Advisors correspondence re. immunization needs in their communities, 1993 June 1-August 31 (Box 1, Folder 1)
        Knight File Number - 1128
        Letters written in the summer of 1993 to Linda Raybin, Knight Foundation Community Initiatives Director, by the Community Advisors in the 26 KF communities. Each advisor's letter outlines the need for an immunization initiative in his/her community. Copies of news articles on local immunization issues are included for some of the cities.
      - Background Information, 1993 September 30-1994 April 26 (Box 1, Folder 2)
        Knight File Number - 4774
        Consists of a letter to KF Advisers from Jim Spaniolo re: results of Immunization Initiative survey; a request for proposals; and background information, both intended to be distributed to potential grantees.
      - Immunization Initiative Grantees' Meetings: Summaries of Presentations, 1994 November 9-1995 November 17 (Box 1, Folder 3)
        Knight File Number - 2727
        Summaries from meetings with grantees of the Knight Foundation's immunization initiative. The goal of the meetings were to help grantees learn about past efforts to increase immunization rates for infants and toddlers and gather informatio from experts in a variety of fields, who offered advice about how to strengthen community=based projects.
      - How to Evaluate the John S. and James L. Knight Foundation Immunization Initiative, 1995 October 5 (Box 1, Folder 4)
        Knight File Number - 4830
        This handbook for grantees was written by consultant Patricia Kelly.
      - Immunization Initiative: Final Report, 1997 June (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
        Knight File Number - 4831
        Data gathered from grantee organizations for a $1.7 million grant used to conduct a range of public awareness and education activities to improve the immunization rates of infants and toddlers. Includes executive summary. (2 folders)
      - Immunization Initiative Transition Grants: Final Report, 2000 January 31 (Box 1, Folder 7)
        Knight File Number - 4264
        Report was prepared by Patricia Kelly of the Kellidge Group. Included are sections on transition grant activities and outcomes; evaluation data on promotional materials; selected grantee data collection tools; and evaluation newsletters.
    - Initiatives - National Community Development (NCDI), 1991-2010; 3.4
      Biographical / Historical
      Phase I of the National Community Development Initiative (1991) was a collaborative effort among J.P. Morgan, The Prudential, Metropolitan Life Foundation, the United States Department of Housing and Urban Development and seven national foundations (Knight Foundation, Rockefeller Foundation, the John D. and Catharine T. Foundation, Pew Charitable Trusts, Surdna Foundation, Annie E. Casey Foundation, and McKnight Foundation). Its purpose was to fund community development corporations nationwide in order to assist neighborhood renewal in 23 cities. Phase II of the initiative was launched in June 1994 to expand the work of the first phase and further strengthen the designated community foundations across the country. Creed Black was named chairman of the initiative in June 1994.
      The files contain memos and correspondence, dating 1993-1995, regarding decisions and actions of NCDI II at meetings, annual meeting books (with budgets, disbursement schedules, work plans, progress reports, and annual reports), legal agreements between funders, approved work plans for individual cities, assessment reports, and conference materials. The press conference briefing materials explain the program and its background.
      - NCDI Promissory Notes, 1991 June 6-1992 July 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
        Knight File Number - 4295
        Four promissory notes from The Enterprise Foundation and the Local Initiatives Support Corporation to the Knight Foundation.
      - Background on NCDI and LISC, 1993 September 21 (Box 1, Folder 2)
        Knight File Number - 1686
        Binder with background material on National Community Development Initiative (NCDI) and LISC for a board discussion. Includes a memo from Jim Pickman giving an overview of the first two years of the first round of NCDI and plans for the second, a memo on NCDI programs in Miami, Philadelphia and St. Paul, a LISC proposal, and newspaper clippings on LISC's work.
      - NCDI Promissory Notes, 1994 August 11 (Box 1, Folder 3)
        Knight File Number - 4296
        Two promissory notes from The Enterprise Foundation and the Local Initiatives Support Corporation to the Knight Foundation.
      - NCDI Assessment Report: Phase I, 1994 November 30 (Box 1, Folder 4)
        Knight File Number - 1052
        Comprehensive Assessment Report: The National Community Development Initiative, Phase I (1991-1994), 11/30/94. Prepared by OMG, Inc., in association with Teamworks, to assess the progress of NCDI.
      - NCDI II, 1994-1997 June (Box 2, Folder 1, Box 1, Folder 5-9)
        Knight File Number - 267
        These folders contain: 1994 Correspondence (decisions and actions at 3rd semi-annual meeting; list of National Community Development Initiative (NCDI) funders, intermediaries, support & assessment team), Annual Meeting Materials (6/15/94, Portland, OR), including materials to formally launch NCDI, Press Conference Briefing Book (3/21/94), NCDI Approved Round II Workplans developed by LISC (7/94-6/97). Box 2 contains 5 file folders: Comprehensive Assessment Report on Phase I (prepared by OMG, 7/95), NCDI II First Semi-Annual Meeting Materials (1/18/95), "Moving to Scale"--An NCDI Working Conference (meeting materials, 2/22/95), NCDI First Annual Meeting Materials (6/13/95).
      - NCDI: Communication Efforts Meeting, 1994 June 25 (Box 2, Folder 2)
        Knight File Number - 1054
        Background materials for the National Community Development Initiative (NCDI) Communication Efforts meeting of 7/7/94. Materials date from 12/10/92-1/6/94, and include memos from past meetings and decisions that were made at those meetings.
      - Greater Miami LISC NCDI II Production, Capacity Building and Advocacy Program, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 3)
        Knight File Number - 1058
        Memo regarding the production, capacity building and advocacy program of the Greater Miami LISC NCDI II, 1994. Includes a program summary, Dade County's community development environment, system gaps, NCDI I activities, program goals, activities and benchmarks, program participants, program funding, program design process, risks and contingencies.
      - NCDI II Legal Agreements, 1994 April 29 (Box 2, Folder 4)
        Knight File Number - 1059
        Legal documents regarding National Community Development Initiative, NCDI II. Includes a Participation Agreement among the funders, Master Loan and Grant Agreement among LISC and the funders, Program Secretary Agreement between Enterprise and James Pickman.
      - NCDI: Miami Summary, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 5)
        Knight File Number - 1055
        Summary of overall strategy, progress, and problems in National Community Development Initiative (NCDI) program in Miami, 1994.
      - NCDI II Assessment, 1994 August 25-December 10 (Box 2, Folder 6)
        Knight File Number - 1053
        Correspondence and reports regarding the National Community Development Initiative II Assessment, 1994. Includes a proposal for the NCDI II Assessment by Harvard University, and an Assessment Design for Phase II of the NDCI by OMG Inc. and Teamworks.
      - NCDI Assessment, 1995 January 14-23 (Box 2, Folder 7)
        Knight File Number - 1049
        Memo from Jim Pickman to National Community Development Initiative (NCDI) participants regarding a meeting on the OMG Assessment Report, which analyzed the NCDI program. Folder also includes an Assessment Overview by OMG/Teamworks, the consultants who wrote the report.
      - NCDI Communications Meeting, 1995 June (Box 2, Folder 8)
        Knight File Number - 1051
        National Community Development Initiative (NCDI) Communications Meeting, Washington, D.C. Background materials for meeting on communications efforts for NCDI, report on Cleveland blitz effort, feasability study and proposal on establishing an NCDI-Hudson Institute sponsored federal policy symposium.
      - NCDI II - Local Initiatives Support Corp. Annual Report, 1995 June 30 (Box 2, Folder 9)
        Knight File Number - 1021
        National Community Development Initiative, NCDI II Local Inititiatives Support Corporation (LISC) Annual Report, June 1995. Includes an overview of LISC's mission (to transform distressed neighborhoods into healthy communities with the help of community development corporations), a management assistance group report, and reports from the participating cities (Bay area, Boston, Chicago, Detroit, Indianapolis, Kansas City, Los Angeles, Miami, New York City, Newark, Philadelphia, Phoenix, Saint Paul, Seattle, and Washington, D.C.).
      - NCDI Communications Program, 1995 January 7-March 18 (Box 2, Folder 10)
        Knight File Number - 1050
        Background materials for a National Community Development Initiative (NCDI) communications meeting, sent by Jim Pickman to participants. The meeting/progress review of the LISC-Enterprise communications effort was held on 1/12/1995 in Newark. The materials include a current status report by the LISC-Enterprise team; a work plan for the communications effort; a proposal for a film. There is also a memo outlining the decisions made at the meeting, and a letter from Creed Black announcing that he will be the NCDI chairman.
      - National Community Development Initiative: Planning for NCDI III, 1995 October 12 (Box 2, Folder 11)
        Knight File Number - 1048
        Confidential memo to NCDI funders from Michael Rubinger and Jim Pickman regarding planning for a possible NCDI III.
      - NCDI, Financial Correspondence, 1995 September 18-November 9 (Box 2, Folder 12)
        Knight File Number - 1047
        Memos from Jim Pickman to National Community Development Initiative (NCDI) funders and intermediaries regarding the program's finances and the proposed human capital initiative.
      - NCDI: "Lessons from the First Three Years" (report), 1995 November 30 (Box 2, Folder 13)
        Knight File Number - 1022
        Report on the National Community Development Initiative (NCDI): "Lessons from the First Three Years," November 1995. Discusses the progress made by community development corporations in the inner cities and poor rural areas of America.
      - NCDI II, First Semi-Annual Meeting Materials, 1995 January 18-19 (Box 3, Folder 1)
        Knight File Number - 1063
        National Community Development Initiative, NCDI II First Semi-Annual Meeting Materials. The meeting was held in Cleveland, OH.
      - "Moving to Scale" - A NCDI Working Conference, 1995 February 22-24 (Box 3, Folder 2)
        Knight File Number - 1062
        Materials from "Moving to Scale"- An National Community Development Initiative (NCDI) Working Conference held in Miami, FL. Includes materials for workshops on: the New Community Development Agenda, Building a Stronger CDC Industry, Building Local Systems that Support Increased Production, A New Vision and New Roles for CDCs, Retaining & Attracting Talented CDC staff, etc.
      - NCDI II First Annual Meeting Materials, 1995 June 13-14 (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
        Knight File Number - 1061
        National Community Development Initiative, NCDI II First Annual Meeting Materials. Meeting was held in Detroit, MI on June 13-15, 1995. The materials include progress reports of NCDI cities and a LISC annual report. 2 folders.
      - NCDI Comprehensive Assessment Report on Phase I, 1995 July 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
        Knight File Number - 1060
        Comprehensive Assessment Report on Phase I of the National Community Development Initiative (NCDI), covering start-up through June, 1994. Prepared by OMG, Inc., in July 1995. Also includes an executive summary which was sent to Knight Foundation advisers.
      - NCDI II, 1996 January 24-25 (Box 4, Folder 1)
        Knight File Number - 1043
        Materials from 2nd annual meeting of NCDI II, held in Atlanta, GA. Includes a schedule, agenda and list of expected attendees, the program secretary's report, sources and uses of funds, human capital status report, planning for NCDI III status report, possible NCDI III: Local Inititiatives Support Corporation (LISC)/Enterprise answers to questions, Financial Management Reports, Fayde Site Visit Report, Enterprise Semi-Annual Report, LISC Semi-Annual Report, recommendations for unallocated $5 million loans, DiPasquale Report, Assessment of Partnership Programs, and Enterprise (EMI) Fannie Mae Program Report.
      - NCDI II, 1996 June 25-26 (Box 4, Folder 2)
        Knight File Number - 1042
        Materials from Second Annual Meeting of NCDI II, held in Los Angeles, CA. Includes a memo from Jim Pickman re. new developments, a schedule, agenda and list of expected attendees, the program secretary's report, sources and uses of funds, human capital status report, planning for NCDI III status report, enterprise annual report, LISC annual report, LISC and Enterprise Financial Management Reports, LISC workplans for $5 million loan, DiPasquale Report, Urban Institute Report, and Enterprise (EMI) Fannie Mae Program Report.
      - NCDI II, 1996 June (Box 4, Folder 3)
        Knight File Number - 1044
        NCDI II Annual Report, submitted by Local Initiatives Support Corporation, June 1996. Includes an overview of the NCDI II program, NCDI local funding/output summaries, and summaries of individual cities.
      - NCDI III: Correspondence and Proposals, 1996 October 31-November 19 (Box 4, Folder 4)
        Knight File Number - 1046
        Memos to NCDI participants from Jim Pickman regarding the review of LISC and Enterprise NCDI III City Proposals. Includes NCDI III proposals from Miami LISC, Detroit LISC, Philadelphia LISC, and St. Paul LISC.
      - NCDI II, 1997 February 4-5 (Box 4, Folder 5)
        Knight File Number - 1045
        Materials from the Third Semi-Annual Meeting of NCDI II, in Dallas, TX. Includes a schedule, agenda, list of expected attendees, program secretary's report, sources and uses of funds (NCDI II), LISC and Enterprise Commitment/Disbursement Schedules, Human Capital, Enterprise (EMI) Fannie Mae Program Report, DiPasquale reports, NCDI III, and Future NCDI Opportunities.
      - NCDI Press Kit, 1997 June 18 (Box 4, Folder 6)
        Knight File Number - 1884
        Press kit for NDCI program, including press releases and fact sheets on the funders and their initiatives.
      - NCDI II Annual Meeting, 1997 June 30 (Box 4, Folder 7)
        Knight File Number - 1883
        Actions and decisions from the NCDI II Annual meeting held in Kansas City, MO on June 25-26, 1997. Memo from Jim Pickman includes announcement of NCDI chair Doug Nelson, dissemination of tax credit report, human capital, NCDPAN, NCDI III workplans and budget, and use of unallocated funds.
      - NCDI II Annex to Master Agreement for NCDI II lenders, 1997 October 7 (Box 5, Folder 1)
        Knight File Number - 1880
        Memo regarding LISC financial portfolio changes.
      - Third Annual Meeting Materials, 1997 June 25-26 (Box 5, Folder 2)
        Knight File Number - 1882